All right. Life is not perfect.
ولكن الحياة ليست دائمًا مثالية.
In some cases,
في بعض الحالات
you may end up getting a bad review or less than a five-star rating,
قد ينتهي بك المطاف بالحصول على مراجعة سيئة أو تقييم أقل من خمس نجوم،
despite your efforts to help the client.
برغم مجهودك في مساعدة العميل.
A bad review could reduce our chances of getting more jobs,
المراجعة السيئة يمكن أن تقلل من فرصك في الحصول على المزيد من الوظائف،
especially if you don't have many reviews,
وخاصة إذا لم يكن لديك العديد من المراجعات السابقة،
but there are a couple of things that you can do to mitigate the risks.
ولكن هناك بضعة أشياء يمكنك القيام بها للتقليل من المخاطر.
First, talk to the client.
أولًا يجب أن تتحدث مع العميل.
If you're not sure of the reason of the low rating or the bad review,
إذا لم تكن متأكدًا من سبب انخفاض التقييم أو سوء المراجعة،
gently ask them if there was something that you could do to make them satisfied,
اسأله بلطف عما إذا كان هناك شيء يمكنك القيام به لإرضائه،
or was there a requirement that was not met.
افهم منه إذا كان لديه طلب لم تقم بعمله.
Try to gauge by talking to the client on what went wrong.
حاول أن تفهم الخطأ الذي حدث عن طريق التحدث مع العميل.
Chances are that they will not respond.
من المحتمل أن لا يرد عليك.
However, if they do respond,
لكن إن رد العميل عليك،
you might get another chance to either fix the problem or give the client
فقد تتوفر لك الفرصة في إصلاح المشكلة أو إعطاء العميل
a reasonable explanation of the cause of the perceived low quality of the job,
تفسير منطقي لتدني جودة العمل،
which may lead to the client changing the review.
وقد يدفع ذلك العميل إلى تغيير مراجعته.
But keep in mind that platforms do not encourage
ولكن ضع في الاعتبار أن المنصات لا تشجع
freelancers to force clients to change their rating.
موظفي العمل الحر على إجبار العملاء لتغيير تقييمهم.
That is why it is important for you to gently ask them
ولهذا من المهم أن تسألهم بلطف
to see if something can be done to improve the rating or review.
لمعرفة إذا كان يمكنك فعل شيء لتحسين التقييم أو المراجعة.
For any bad review,
بالنسبة للمراجعة السيئة،
some platforms remove the review if you give a 100 percent refund to the client.
فبعض المنصات تمحو المراجعة إذا أعدت 100% من المقابل المالي للعميل.
You don't get paid for the work you did,
فلا تحصل على أجر للعمل الذي قمت به،
and hence you don't get a bad review.
ومن ثم لا تحصل على مراجعة سيئة.
Alternatively, you could also try a partial refund.
كبديل يمكنك أيضًا محاولة إعادة جزء من المال.
For example, you could do a 50 percent refund to the client.
على سبيل المثال، يمكنك إعادة 50% للعميل.
In this case, the platform may not remove the review,
وفي هذه الحالة لا يجوز للمنصة أن تزيل المراجعة،
but the client may be okay to reconsider the review.
ولكن قد يشجع هذا العميل على التفكير في تغيير مراجعته.
Sometimes you know that you have done a good job,
أحيانًا تكون متأكدًا أنك قمت بعمل جيد،
but the client is difficult to be convinced.
ولكن من الصعب إقناع العميل.
In this case, you may not be willing to give a refund to the client,
في هذه الحالة قد لا تريد إعادة المال للعميل،
especially if the money involved is sizable.
وخاصة إذا كان المبلغ المالي كبير.
In that case, it is okay to approach the support team
وفي هذه الحالة لا بأس من التواصل مع فريق الدعم
of the freelancing platform and explain them your case.
على منصة العمل الحر، وشرح الموقف لهم.
If they are indeed convinced,
فإذا اقتنع فريق الدعم بكلامك،
they may be willing to remove the review for you.
فقد يكونوا على استعداد لإزالة المراجعة.
Sometimes you may indeed have messed
في بعض الأحيان قد تكون قد أسأت العمل بالفعل
up and the client is justified in leaving a bad review,
وعندها تكون مراجعة العميل السيئة أمر له تبريره،
or even if you did a good job,
أو حتى لو قمت بعمل جيد،
the platform or the client may not be willing to edit or remove the review.
قد لا تكون المنصة أو العميل على استعداد لتغيير المراجعة أو إزالتها.
It's okay to accept that and move on.
فلا بأس من قبول ذلك والمضي قدمًا.
Life is not always fair.
الحياة ليست عادلة دائمًا.
If you get a lot of other good reviews,
إذا حصلت على الكثير من المراجعات الجيدة الأخرى،
this one bad review,
فهذه المراجعة السيئة،
may not count that much.
لن تكون لها قيمة كبيرة.
Though it may get difficult to get your next client,
على الرغم من أنه قد يكون من الصعب الحصول عميل قادم،
and you may have to put in some extra effort there.
وقد تضطر إلى بذل بعض الجهد الإضافي للحصول على العميل القادم.
If a new client asks you about
إذا سألك العميل الجديد عن
the bad review and they find your explanation within reason,
المراجعة السيئة ووجد تفسيرك منطقي،
they might be okay to try you out.
فقد لا يمانع تجربة العمل معك.